JAYLEN WANG

Carnegie Mellon University Email: jaylenw@andrew.cmu.edu

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Web: https://jaylenwang7.github.io

BRIEF BIOGRAPHY

My work bridges computer architecture and software systems, demonstrating the importance of that bridge in enabling sustainable data center systems via solutions that span the compute stack.

As the demand for web services continues to grow, data centers are scaling up to meet the demand, consuming a massive amount of energy and producing significant carbon emissions. My research focuses on addressing the growing carbon emissions, produced both by running and manufacturing hardware, of data centers by analyzing inefficiencies across computer architecture and software systems and designing solutions to make these systems more energy and carbon efficient.

My work is one of the first to examine the environmental impact of hyperscale web systems and to provide actionable insights to reduce it. My work integrates carbon efficiency into computer system design, as it is crucial for sustainable growth and access to critical web services in both developed and developing nations. My work is a step towards curbing computing's contributions towards climate change and promoting sustainable computing practices.

My research has been recognized with the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP) Award, the 2023 Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship, a Ford Foundation 2023 Predoctoral Fellowship Competition Honorable Mention, and the Jack and Mildred Bowers Scholarship in Engineering.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Electrical and Computer Engineering

Carnegie Mellon University

Aug 2022 - Present

NSF GRFP Fellow

Dissertation Title: Enabling Sustainable Web Systems

B.Sc., Electrical Engineering

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

PIs: Profs. David Brooks & Gu-Yeon Wei

Minor in Computer Science

Graduated Summa Cum Laude (GPA: 4.0/4.0); Member of Phi Beta Kappa

Harvard University Aug 2018 - May 2022

AWARDS AND HONORS

Jack and Mildred Bowers Scholarship in Engineering Full tuition support for third year of PhD	2024
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP) Award Winner Awarded \$171,000 as part of prestigious fellowship supporting exceptional graduate students in STEM	2023
Ford Foundation 2023 Predoctoral Fellowship Competition Honorable Mention Honorable mention given to top Ford Fellowship candidates	2023
Benjamin Garver Lamme/Westinghouse Graduate Fellowship Full tuition support for second year of PhD	2023
Carnegie Institute of Technology Dean's Fellow Awarded \$83,000 towards tuition, stipend, and travel	2022
Harvard SEAS Dean's Engineering Design Award Awarded \$500 for having one of the top 7 (out of 43) best Senior engineering design projects	2022
Sophia Freund Prize Awarded \$1000 as highest ranking undergraduate in the Electrical Engineering department	2022
Phi Beta Kappa Member Admitted into Harvard's chapter, one of 146 out of 1962 (7.4%) students	2022

Derek Bok Center Distinction in Teaching Awarded to most highly rated (by students) TAs; received distinction in three semesters John Harvard Scholar Award given to top 5% (4.0 GPA) of students in respective class Harvard College Research Program Funding Recipient Awarded \$3,500 to perform independent research during the summer Detur Prize Winner Recognizes students with top academic standing in their first year at Harvard

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE AND JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Jaylen Wang, Daniel S. Berger, Fiodar Kazhamiaka, Celine Irvene, Chaojie Zhang, Esha Choukse, Kali Frost, Rodrigo Fonseca, Brijesh Warrier, Chetan Bansal, Jonathan Stern, Ricardo Bianchini, and Akshitha Sriraman. Designing Cloud Servers for Lower Carbon. 51st International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA 2024). June 2024.

PEER-REVIEWED WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

- Jaylen Wang, Melissa Pan, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Giving Old Servers New Life at Hyperscale. 6th Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2024) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. June 2024.
- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Peeling Back the Carbon Curtain: Carbon Optimization Challenges in Cloud Computing. 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Computer Systems (HotCarbon 2023). July 2023.

Performs the first ever characterization of server generations for microservice-based web services to enable hardware lifetime extension

- Jialun Lyu, Jaylen Wang, Kali Frost, Chaojie Zhang, Celine Irvene, Esha Choukse, Rodrigo Fonseca, Ricardo Bianchini, Fiodar Kazhamiaka, and Daniel S. Berger. Myths and Misconceptions Around Reducing Embedded Carbon for Cloud Platforms. 2nd Workshop on Sustainable Computer Systems (HotCarbon 2023). July 2023.
- Jaylen Wang, Udit Gupta, and Akshitha Sriraman. Giving Old Servers New Life at Hyperscale. 1st Workshop on Hot Topics in System Infrastructure (HotInfra 2023) held in conjunction with ISCA. June 2023.
- Sahana Rangarajan, Jaylen Wang, Sara Mahdizadeh Shahri, Pratyush Patel, and Akshitha Sriraman.
 Designing Equitable Data Center Scheduling Systems. Career Workshop for Inclusion and Diversity in Computer Architecture (CWIDCA 2022) held in conjunction with MICRO. Oct 2022.

Introduces equity as a first-order design metric in modern data center scheduling systems

Jaylen Wang, Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Gu-Yeon Wei, and David Brooks. A Dataflow-Aware Fault Resilience Analysis Framework for Deep Neural Network Accelerators. 4th Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2021) held in conjunction with ASPLOS. March 2022.

Introduces a new framework and tool to quickly and accurately assess the reliability of deep neural network accelerator designs to random bit flips, providing insights for resilient accelerator design

INVITED SEMINAR TALKS

Designing Cloud Servers for Lower Carbon

– Google SystemsResearch@Google (SRG) Group, Host: Dr. David Culler	Sep 2024
- ISCA, Buenos Aires	Jun 2024
- University of California San Diego (CSE), Host: Prof. Jishen Zhao	Apr 2024

- University of California Riverside (ECE), Host: Prof. Shaolei Ren

Apr 2024

AWARDED GRANT PROPOSALS COLLABORATED ON

 AWS Cloud Credit for Research, "Carbon-Aware Scheduling to Reduce Hyperscale Carbon Emissions", Award: \$76,000, Award period: 2024-25

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE/IMPACT

Co-organizer/founder of workshop or panel

- Panel Co-Organizer for Panel on Sustainable Systems at The 19th Workshop on
 Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS 2023)

 Feb 2023

Invited contributor, speaker, or panelist

- Graduate Student Panelist for Undergrad Architecture Mentoring Workshop (uArch)
 Jun 2024
 held in conjunction with ISCA

Artifact evaluation committee member

- Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS 2024) Oct 2023
- International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO 2024)

 Sep 2024

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

IBM Research Intern, IBM Research, Yorktown Heights, NY

May 2024 - August 2024

Mentor: Asser Tantawi

Developing new frameworks and strategies for more sustainable cross-cluster batch job scheduling.

Azure Systems Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA

May 2023 - August 2023

Mentor: Fiodar Kazhamiaka

Developing a framework based on an understanding of server design's data center-scale impact to improve Azure's resource and carbon efficiency.

Graduate Research Assistant, Carnegie Mellon University

Aug 2022 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Akshitha Sriraman

Introducing sustainability as a first-order hardware/software system design metric for hyperscale systems and redesigning data center systems to promote hardware reuse

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

March 2021 - Aug 2022

Lab: Harvard Architecture, Circuits, and Compilers Group

Advisors: Dr. Abdulrahman Mahmoud, Profs. Gu-Yeon Wei and David Brooks

Developing a hardware-aware framework for analyzing the resilience of deep neural network accelerators to soft errors, considering the reuse of values in an accelerator's dataflow propagation

Engineering Development Group Intern, MathWorks

May 2021 - Aug 2021

Team: Deep Learning HDL Toolbox Supervisors: Wang Chen, Siyuan Xu

Enabling efficient mapping of non-square convolution kernels onto square processing-element arrays, allowing users to deploy models using non-square kernels onto FPGAs

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2020 - Aug 2020

Lab: Harvard Edge Computing Lab Advisor: Prof. Vijay Janapa Reddi

Analyzing how using SLAM for localization affects efficiency and power usage within autonomous drone applications by integrating SLAM algorithms into an open-sourced drone benchmarking framework

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Harvard University

May 2019 - Aug 2019

Lab: Hoffman Physics Lab Advisor: Prof. Jenny Hoffman

Developing a tensioning system for an XY-walker system to extend the range of a scanning tunneling microscope used to research the proximity effect of superconductivity

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Invited guest lecture on sustainable computing

- Computer Systems & the Hardware-Software Interface (18-344); Profs. Akshitha Sriraman & Fall 2024 & Brandon Lucia

Undergraduate teaching assistant, Harvard University

_	Systems Programming and Machine Organization (CS 61); Prof. Eddie Kohler	Fall 2020, 2021
-	Circuits, Devices, and Transduction (ES 152); Profs. Gage Hills & Woodward Yang	Fall 2021
-	Systems and Control (ES 150); Profs. Li Na & Yue Lu	Fall 2021
_	Introduction to Electrical Engineering (ES 50); Profs. Chris Lombardo & Marko Loncar	Spring 2021
_	Integration, Series and Differential Equations (MATH 1B); Dr. Hakim Walker	Fall 2019

LEADERSHIP & VOLUNTEERING

- CMU Institute of Technology K-12 Outreach, STEM Volunteer	$2023 ext{-}Present$
- President of Harvard Club Tennis	2019-2022
 President of Harvard College Engineering Society 	2020-2021
 Co-President of Harvard Engineering Peer Concentration Advisors 	2020-2021

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages	C/C++, Python, Shell, Verilog, x86 Assembly
System Skills	Low-level Systems Programming, Performance Characterization,
Tools and Frameworks	Scripting, Docker Pin, gem5, Linux perf, Intel PMU tools, PyTorch, Catapult HLS, Git

REFERENCES

- 1. Prof. Akshitha Sriraman (akshitha@cmu.edu) Assistant Professor, Carnegie Mellon University
- 2. Daniel S. Berger (daberg@microsoft.com)
 Researcher in Azure Systems Research Group, Microsoft
- 3. Fiodar Kazhamiaka (fkazhamiaka@microsoft.com) Researcher in Azure Systems Research Group, Microsoft
- 4. Prof. David Brooks (dbrooks@g.harvard.edu) Haley Family Professor of Computer Science, Harvard University
- 5. Prof. Udit Gupta (ugupta@cornell.edu) Assistant Professor, Cornell University